(Questioner) I have some conflict
at home over my marriage plan.
(Questioner) I am not married yet but am
planning to marry a foreigner boyfriend.
(Questioner) My parents are rather
touchy about this.
(Questioner) They seem to be saying,
"Just where did you come from?"
(Questioner) They are wavering back and
forth even after having given an approval.
(Questioner) They are very upset and
in great distress.
(Questioner) They tell me that they dislike
me because I am not listening to them.
(Questioner) I am, however,
not willing to change my mind.
(Questioner) But I feel guilty
witnessing their distress.
(Questioner) Because of this,
I end up feeling guilty over
(Questioner) other things
taking on more guilt.
Did you expect your mother to welcome
your decision to marry a foreigner?
Didn't you foresee that your parents
would not approve or would feel hurt?
Didn't you make a decision in spite of
knowing how they would react?
Then, there is no reason for you
to suffer because they are hurting.
You expected this after all.
(Questioner) Is there anything I can do?
No need to do anything.
Parents can endure a bit of pain.
Why? They gave birth to you without
your permission. (Applause)
This is the karmic consequence
for having you.
It's fine. You are not guilty
of anything.
You are not guilty.
Your mother's crying over you
marrying a foreigner
is her business.
Ethically or scientifically,
you are not guilty.
Not even according to the teachings of
Buddha, are you guilty.
So, no need to worry.
Even when she is hurting, leave her alone.
Look upon her as a grandmother next door.
(Applause) Just observe that
she is having a hard time
because her daughter
is marrying a foreigner.
It is your weakness in spiritual practice if
you suffer seeing your mother's heartache.
If your practice is solid, you would
see her pain with equanimity.
It is not your fault.
You didn't steal or kill.
You didn't commit adultery.
You didn't lie.
You didn't' use drugs or smoke cigarettes.
You did not do anything wrong.
It derives from the cultural value system
to which she is very attached.
You can't do anything about it.
From her standpoint,
is she doing anything wrong?
She is not doing anything wrong either.
In other words, neither you nor your mom
is wrong about anything.
"Mom must be hurting,"
"Given her age, her ethical, moral, and
cultural background, she could be hurt,"
Just understand her this way.
Though understanding, there is nothing
you can do for her.
Nothing at all.
The only thing you might be able to
do is to say you're sorry.
Not because you did anything wrong,
after all the work of raising you,
she seems to be hurt because of you .
When Buddha left home, his parents
must have felt awful, right?
They were really hurt.
Then, Buddha should have given up his
practice and wept for his parents, or no??
No, he had to be steadfast
in his practice.
So, don't worry about
your parents' reactions.
There is nothing for you
to do to rectify the situation.
The only thing you can do is
for you to marry this foreigner
and continue your Buddhist practice
sincerely so that you'd be able to overcome
any hardships and live a happy life with
your husband. Then things will work out.
It does not help your mom
if you cry and suffer now.
Otherwise, you could call off the wedding
and marry a Korean man.
If you are truly concerned about your
mother, you ought to marry a Korean guy.
But if you think that your life is
more important, there is no need
for you to cry for your mom.
Are you really worried about your mom?
Not really, right?
(Applause)
So, stop being hypocritical.
Your sorrow is hypocritical.
Why pretend when you are unwilling
to do anything for your mother?
Others might believe you are a devoted
dutiful daughter. (Applause)
Just accept yourself as an undutiful
daughter for now.
You'd be showing your gratitude
to her by living a happy life.
If you get married in this state, you might
end up regretting when going gets tough.
"Oh, I should have listened to Mom,"
"I shouldn't have married
over her objection, "
This shows that you are not willing to accept
the responsibility for your own choice.
You are trying to avoid
responsibility of the future.
Just tell your mom, " I am sorry Mom;
I understand how you feel,"
"But this choice, I make."
"I am sorry to hurt you but there is
nothing I can do about this."
In other word, there is
no room for negotiation.
"I am going to repay the debt of gratitude
to you someday by living a happy life."
Leave it at that.
Don't expect your mom's consent
or blessings for your marriage.
Accept that your mom has the right to
weep and disapprove of your marriage.
Don't contest it.
Just smile and say,"I am sorry, mom,"
If you cry and apologize,
that is fraudulent.
Say, "I am sorry" as you're smiling.
"I know how you feel, but this is what
I want. And it's my life."
You have be somewhat thick skinned.
"If you don't want to,
you don't have to say yes."
"You don't have to help
with the wedding expenses either."
Are you looking to receive some help
financially for the wedding?
OK, you're not. That is the right way.
Not getting help doesn't mean
that you can dismiss them either.
Whether or not they support you,
you owe them a debt of
gratitude as your parents.
So, don't pretend like you're such
a good girl by crying. (Applause)
Don't pretend, be shameless.
If anyone asks, say,
"What have I done wrong?"
"Did I kill someone? Did I steal?"
"Did I commit adultery? Did I lie?
Did I use foul language?"
"I've acted in accordance with
Buddha's precepts, what have I done wrong?
Go forward with shameless confidence
But you must understand
your mother's feelings.
Be grateful whether or not
you receive help from her.
Then, get married and live well.
(Applause)